Whitman College student publications collection 1883-2017
Whitman College and Northwest Archives
Whitman College student publications collection
1883-2017
Whitman College and Northwest Archives 345 Boyer Avenue Walla Walla, WA 99362 Archives@whitman.edu https://library.whitman.edu/archives/
Whitman College
WCA142
64.25 linear feet
This collection contains publications created by Whitman College students and student organizations. Included are student newspapers, literary journals, zines and magazines.
Collection is open for research.
On December 20, 1859, Reverend Cushing Eells convinced the Washington Territorial Legislature to grant a charter to form the Whitman Seminary in honor of his fellow missionaries Marcus and Narcissa Whitman. By 1866, construction of an initial two-story building was completed and the school opened in the city of Walla Walla. On November 28, 1883, the legislature issued a new charter, transforming the seminary into a four-year degree-granting private college.
This collection contains literary journals, magazines, zines, newspapers and other publications produced by Whitman College students. The publications included in this collection include: Blue Moon, Break Ground, Carbon-14, The Circuit, The Clock Tower, The Codex, Faire, The Genius, Hey Man, Masque, The Narrator, The Sheet, The Whitman College Pioneer, Quarterlife, Queering, The Secession, The Source, Whitman Academic Journal, The Whitman Collegian, Whitman Wire and Yeast.
Whitman College
Walla Walla (Wash.)
Student publications; College students' writings; College students
Colleges and Universities; Student Life
- Blue Moon, 1924-2017; Series 1 (Box 1, Folder 1-41, Box 2, Folder 1-16)
  Blue Moon is a literary magazine published by Whitman College students. Published annually since 1924, with a hiatus from 1932-1989, the student-run publication features poetry, prose, and art submitted by the Whitman community. Blue Moon won the 2012 Columbia Scholastic Press Gold Crown and the College Magazine Silver Crown awards.
  This series contains issues of the Blue Moon, some financial records of the publication from 1924, and a collaboration issue between Quaterlife and the Blue Moon called Conclu[e]sive from 2012. There is also one undated issue of an experimental off-shoot publication called "Blue Mooner."
- Break Ground, 2012; Series 2 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  Published in 2012, Break Gound is a collection of stories, essays, letters, poems and art that revolves around the topic of sexual assault. The writers of Break Gound were inspired to construct a magazine that would facilitate important discussions and a space for reflection in the hopes of changing our culture over time.
  This series contains one issue of Break Ground.
- Carbon-14, 1990-1991; Series 3 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  Carbon-14 was a student-run publication from the early 1990s. It was published bi-monthly from October 1990 until January 1991. A group of around 20 students got together to start a publication that contained an eclectic mix of contemporary thoughts, poems, essays, cartoons, recipes and more. The editors and staff noted that Carbon-14 was written less with the intention of producing an actual paper and was instead more process-oriented.
  This series contains a bound copy and unbound copies of the complete run of Carbon-14.
- The Circuit, 2011-2017; Series 4 (Box 4, Folder 1-17)
  The Circuit is a publication of the Whitman Wire that was started in the fall of 2011. The Wire staff wanted to create another space for expressing creative ideas and individual voices. They release themed issues that range from "The Home Issue" to "The Graduation Issue" that contain photos, essays, reviews, crossword puzzles and horoscopes.
  This series contains issues of the The Circuit magazine.
- The Clock Tower, 1939-1955; Series 5 (Box 5, Folder 1-47)
  The Clock Tower was first published in 1939. This literary magazine features short fiction, articles, letters, original humor and cartoons.
  This series contains issues of the The Clock Tower literary magazine.
- The Codex, 1916-1921; Series 6 (Box 3, Folder 2-5)
  The Codex was a magazine published by Whitman Students from 1916-1921. It features short stories, poetry, essays and other forms of writing. The Codex was written with the intention of sharing the written work of the college as a whole rather than any single department.
  This series contaisn issues of The Codex magazine.
- Faire, 1973-1987; Series 7 (Box 6, Folder 1-23)
  Faire was a fine arts magazine from 1974-1987. It was published three times a year and includes a variety of poetry, photographs, visual art and creative writing.
  This series contains issues of the magazine Faire.
- The Genius, 1948 May; Series 8 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  The Genius: Western Students Graphic Arts Quarterly was a magazine created to share and advertize the written and visual works of college students around the western region. It contains a variety of paintings, photographs, short fiction and poetry.
  This series contains one issue of The Genius: Western Students Graphic Arts Quarterly.
- Hey Man, 2010-2011; Series 9 (Box 7, Folder 2-4)
  Hey Man was a monthly magazine published by the staff members of KWCW, the college's radio station. It was dedicated to all things music, and includes album reviews, interviews, concert reviews and personal recommendations.
  This series contains issues of the music magazine Hey Man.
- Masque, 1958-1970; Series 10 (Box 8, Folder 1-15)
  Masque was a literary magazine from the late 1950s that featured writing and artwork that was considered by some, to be the best from the college at the time. The staff was lead by Gerald Cohen, an instructor in English and French, and Richard Rasmussen an Associate Professor of Art.
  This series contains issues of the literary magazine Masque, a calendar the staff produced and a newspaper article reviewing the fifth issue of the publication.
- The Narrator, 1969; Series 11 (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  The Narrator was an independent student run, non-profit newspaper that was first published on January 29, 1969. The editors and writers were trying to create a newspaper that differed from the student newspaper, the Pioneer, and allowed for different perspectives. The publication had an emphasis on improving student-faculty-administration communication, and providing a diverse spectrum of student voices. The Narrator was published throughout the spring of 1969, and the staff produced its final issue on April 30, 1969.
  This series contains issues of the newspaper The Narrator, as well as the publication's charter that was passed by the Associated Students of Whitman College.
- The Sheet, 1929-1985; Series 12 (Box 10, Folder 1-7)
  The Sheet was a newsletter-style publication written anonymously by members of the outlawed fraternity, Tau Nu Epsilon, in the 1930s. The publication contained humorous commentary on taboo topics, and each issue was dedicated to revealing a scandal on campus.
  This series contains the One Sheet, Four Sheet, Five Sheet and Six Sheet, as well as a related publication, Bally Hoo. Also included are newspaper clippings and correspondence related to kidnappings carried out by Tau Nu Epsilon, in response to student election coaltions.
- Whitman College Pioneer, 1896-2016; Series 13 (Box 15, Box 16, Box 17, Box 18, Box 19, Box 20, Box 21, Box 22, Box 23, Box 24, Box 25, Box 26, Box 27, Box 28, Box 29, Box 30, Box 31, Box 32, Box 33, Box 34, Box 35, Box 36, Box 37, Box 38, Box 39, Box 40, Box 41, Box 42, Box 43, Box 44, Box 45, Box 46, Box 47, Box 48, Box 49, Box 50, Box 51, Box 52, Box 53, Box 54)
  The Whitman College Pioneer was a student-run newspaper. The Pioneer was published weekly since 1896. Issues covered campus news, sports, arts, special events, and more. The name of the newspaper was changed to the Whitman Wire over the summer of 2016, because the editorial staff believed that the paper's name no longer reflected Whitman's mission and campus culture.
  This series contains issues of the Whitman College Pioneer. Also included are receipts, stationary and a style book from the early 1900s. There is some correspondence about controversial articles included in the newspaper.
- Quarterlife, 2006-2017; Series 14 (Box 11, Folder 1-45)
  Quarterlife is a student literary journal published four times a year. It includes submissions of poetry, prose, sketches, photos, and other art works by the Whitman community. The issues have topical themes such as "Honey" and "Gas Stations." The publication was founded in 2006 on the belief that everyone is a writer, and everyone has a message to share.
  This series contains issues of the literary journal Quaterlife.
- Queering, Undated; Series 15 (Box 10, Folder 8-10)
  Queering is a publication focused on empowering the LGBTQ community on campus. It was published as a safe space to facilitate and engage in conversation about queer issues. The writing and visual art comes from students of all sexual orientations and backgrounds.
  This series contains volumes 1, 3 and 5 of the publication Queering.
- The Secession and Succession, 2009; 2011; Series 16 (Box 7, Folder 5-8)
  The Secession was a magazine that featured short essays, comics and cartoons. It was created with the intention of providing an open space for creative works that was less selective than other campus publications. In 2011, the named changed to The Succession.
  This series contains four issues of The Secession, and three issues of The Succession. It is not a complete run of the publications.
- The Source, 1979-1993; Series 17 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  The Source was an annual publication that featured reviews and critiques of a handful of courses from each department. The mission of this catalog was to work towards improving classes while providing a glimpse into the Whitman education system.
  Background information and research materials that students used to create The Source can be found in the Associated Students of Whitman College records.
  This series contains issues of the The Source publication. This is not a complete run of the publication, as there are missing issues.
- Whitman Academic Journal, 2000; Series 18 (Box 13, Folder 1)
  The Whitman Academic Journal was an annual publication that was dedicated to student research, with submissions from the majority of departments on campus. The first issue was published in the spring 2000.
  This series only contains the first issue of the Whitman Academic Journal.
- The Whitman Collegian, 1883; Series 19 (Box 13, Folder 2-6)
  The Whitman College Collegian was created in 1893 as the college's first student run newspaper. It was published once a month from January to May 1893.
  This series contains all five issues of the Whitman Collegian.
- Whitman Wire, 2016-2017; Series 20 (Box 55)
  The name of Whitman College's student newspaper was changed from the Whitman College Pioneer to the Whitman Wire over the summer of 2016, because the editorial staff believed that the paper's name no longer reflected Whitman's mission and campus culture. They argued that the term "Pioneer" was and is symbolic of a celebratory story of white settlers taking land from the Cayuse, Walla Walla, and Umatilla peoples.
  This series contains issues of the Whitman Wire.
- Yeast, 1935-1939; Series 21 (Box 14, Folder 1-18)
  Yeast was a literary magazine that was created after the end of Blue Moon in 1933.The work consists of poetry, short essays, and fiction. It was sponsored by students from Whitman College but accepted contributions from other schools. The main purpose was to spark creativity and a desire to write within its readers.
  This series contains a bound copy and unbound copies of Yeast magazine.